Michael Zingale / Curriculum Vitæ

Department of Physics and Astronomy, Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY 11794-3800 phone: (631) 632-8225 e-mail: michael.zingale@stonybrook.edu

> web: http://www.astro.sunysb.edu/mzingale/ github: https://github.com/zingale youtube: https://www.youtube.com/user/michaelzingale

Present Position:

Jan. 2012-Associate Professor of Physics and Astronomy, Stony Brook University, Stony Brook,

Research Interests:

I am interested in developing and applying computational hydrodynamics algorithms to problems in nuclear astrophysics. A large part of this work is the development of low Mach number hydrodynamics algorithms suited toward long-time evolution in astrophysical flows. The low Mach number simulation code Maestro (developed together with collaborators at LBNL) has been applied to a variety of problems to model convection in stellar environments, including Type Ia supernovae, X-ray bursts, novae, and massive star evolution. Maestro is publicly available.

Education:

2000	Ph.D. in Astronomy and Astrophysics, University of Chicago thesis: Helium Detonations on Neutron Stars advisor: Dr. J. W. Truran
1998	M.S. in Astronomy and Astrophysics, University of Chicago
1996	B.S. in Physics and Astronomy, University of Rochester, Magna Cum Laude thesis: Magnetohydrodynamical Wave Support of Molecular Clouds Minor in Mathematics, University of Rochester

Academic Appointments:

2014–	Affiliate, Institute for Advanced Computational Science, Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, NY
2006–2011	Assistant Professor of Physics and Astronomy, Stony Brook University
2001–2005	Postdoctoral Researcher, SciDAC Supernova Science Center, University of California, Santa Cruz. Worked on simulations of turbulent thermonuclear flames in Type Ia supernova. Initiated a collaboration with Lawrence Berkeley Lab to apply low Mach number hydrodynamics methods to astrophysical flames. advisor: Dr. S. E. Woosley
2000–2001	Research Associate, Center for Astrophysical Thermonuclear Flashes, University of Chicago. One of the developers of the FLASH Code. Research focused on flame simulations in Type Ia supernovae. advisor: Dr. J. W. Truran

1997-2000	Graduate student researcher, Center for Astrophysical Thermonuclear Flashes and
	Department of Astronomy and Astrophysics, University of Chicago. One of the
	developers of the FLASH Code. advisor: Dr. J. W. Truran

Honors / Awards:

Scialog Fellow for Scialog: Time Domain Astrophysics: Stars and Explosions
Presidential Early Career Award in Science and Engineering (PECASE). Nomination through DOE NNSA.
DOE Office of Nuclear Physics Outstanding Junior Investigator (OJI) Award for a proposal entitled: <i>Multidimensional Modeling of Astrophysical Thermonuclear Explosions</i>
Gordon Bell Award in High Performance Computing, Special Category for a paper entitled <i>High-Performance Reactive Fluid Flow Simulations Using Adaptive Mesh Refinement on Thousands of Processors</i> , Calder et al. 2000. (SC 2000 conference)
Carl Sagan Award for Excellence in Teaching (Dept. of Astronomy & Astrophysics, University of Chicago)
Gregor Wentzel graduate teaching award (Dept. of Physics, University of Chicago)
Stoddard Prize in physics for senior thesis (University of Rochester)
Flagg Award for highest GPA in physics (University of Rochester)
Inducted into Phi Beta Kappa honor society (University of Rochester)
Inducted into Sigma Pi Sigma physics honor society (University of Rochester)

Publications:

60+ refereed publications and conference proceedings, h-index = 19 (ISI)

Research Grants/Contracts as Principal Investigator:

2011–2013	Department of Energy, Office of Nuclear Physics (2.5-year renewal), Multidimensional Modeling of Astrophysical Thermonuclear Explosions, DOE DE-FG02-06ER41448	\$253,000
2010–2011	Contract with Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, <i>Multi-dimensional Modeling of Nova with Realistic Nuclear Physics</i> , 2010: B589924; 2011: B593287	\$ 99,768
2009–2011	Department of Energy, Office of Nuclear Physics Outstanding Junior Investigator Award (2-year renewal), <i>Multidimensional Modeling of Astrophysical Thermonuclear Explosions</i> , DOE DE-FG02-06ER41448	\$186,000
2007–2009	Contract with Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, <i>Verification and Validation of Radiation Hydrodynamics for Astrophysical Applications</i> , 2007: B568673; 2008: B574691; 2009 B582735	\$150,000

	5	
2006–2009	Department of Energy, Office of Nuclear Physics Outstanding Junior Investigator Award, Multidimensional Modeling of Astrophysical Thermonuclear Explosions, DOE DE-FG02-06ER41448	\$255,000
Research Gra	nts/Contracts as Co-Investigator:	
2015–2018	Department of Energy, Office of Nuclear Physics Research in Nuclear Astrophysics: Supernovae, Compact Objects, and Algorithms, DOE DE-FG02-87ER40317, PI: James Lattimer, Co-Is: Alan Calder, Michael Zingale	\$1,100,000
2013–2015	Department of Energy, Office of Nuclear Physics Research in Nuclear Astrophysics: Supernovae, Compact Objects, and Algorithms, DOE DE-FG02-87ER40317, PI: James Lattimer, Co-Is: Alan Calder, Michael Zingale	\$640,000
2012–2015	NSF, White Dwarf Mergers as Progenitors of Type Ia Supernovae, AST-1211563, PI: Alan Calder, Co-Is: Doug Swesty, Michael Zingale	\$437,643
Large Compu	ter Time Allocations:	
2015–16	PI on an INCITE 2015 award for the OLCF Cray XK7 titan machine entitled <i>Approaching Exascale Models of Astrophysical Explosions</i> (2015: 50 Mh, 2016: 55 Mh)	
2011–2015	Co-I on NSF PRAC for NCSA/Blue Waters, Type Ia Supernoval hours)	e (9.1 M node
2015	PI on a NERSC 2015 allocation, <i>Three-dimensional studies of conv bursts</i> (5.9 M MPP hours)	ection in X-ray
2014	PI on a NERSC 2014 allocation, <i>Three-dimensional studies of conv bursts</i> (14 M MPP hours)	ection in X-ray
2014	Co-I on a NERSC 2014 allocation, <i>Type Ia Supernovae and X-Ray Bullocation</i>)	ersts (9 M MPI
2012–2014	Co-I on an INCITE 2012 award for the OLCF Cray XT5 for a proposal entitled <i>Petascale Simulations of Type Ia Supernovae</i> (2012: 46 Mh; 2013: 55 Mh; 2014: 50 Mh)	
2013	PI on XSEDE allocation on Kraken/NICS, CASTRO Simulations of Dwarfs (4.1 Mh)	Merging White
2013	Co-I on a NERSC 2013 allocation, Type Ia Supernovae and X-ray Burnhours)	sts (3.5 M MPI
2011	Co-I on a TeraGrid allocation on the Kraken machine for a pro Thermonuclear Bursts on the Surfaces of Compact Astrophysical Object 2011)	1
2011	Co-I on an INCITE 2011 award for the Cray XT5/ORNL for a pro Petascale Simulations of Type Ia Supernovae (50 Mh)	oposal entitlec

2010	PI on a TeraGrid allocation on the Kraken machine for a proposal entitled <i>Thermonuclear Bursts on the Surfaces of Compact Astrophysical Objects</i> (1 Mh; Oct. 2010)
2010	Co-I on an INCITE 2010 award for the Cray XT5/ORNL for a proposal entitled <i>Multidimensional Models of Type Ia Supernovae from Ignition to Observables</i> (5 Mh initially + 20 Mh supplement)
2007–2009	Co-Investigator on an INCITE 2007 award for the Cray XT3/ORNL for a proposal entitled <i>First Principles Models of Type Ia Supernovae</i> . (2007: 4 Mh; 2008: 3.5 Mh; 2009: 3 Mh)
2006	Co-Principal Investigator on the Leadership Computing Facility (ORNL) allocation entitled <i>Ignition and Flame Propagation in Type Ia Supernovae.</i> (3 Mh)

Stony Brook Physics and Astronomy Teaching Experience:

Astronomy Today (AST 100)	A one-credit undergraduate seminar on current astronomy topics, where students lead the discussion on current topics. (F 2010, F 2011, F 2014, F 2015)
Introduction to the Solar System (AST 105)	An overview of solar system topics (solar system dynamics, Kepler's laws, planetary processes, exoplanets,) for non-majors. (F 2007, F 2008, F 2009, F 2011, S 2014, S 2015)
Astronomy (AST 203)	A calculus-based introduction to astronomy and astrophysics for majors, covering the basics of radiation, spectra, binary stars, stellar evolution, ISM, clusters, galaxies, and cosmology. (S 2007, S 2008, S 2009, S 2010, S 2011, S 2012)
Introduction to Planetary Sciences (AST 205)	A calculus-based introduction to the solar system for majors covering basic solar system motion, planetary processes, exoplanets, and solar system formation. (F 2010, F 2014)
Stars (PHY 521)	A graduate-level introduction to the physical processes inside stars. (F 2013, F 2015)
The Application of Simulation in Astrophysics (grad special topics)	Develop the equations of hydrodynamics, instabilities common in astrophysics, and discuss numerical methods for solving the Euler equations (finite-volume methods, Riemann solvers, etc.) (S 2006)
Numerical Methods for (Astro)Physics (grad special topics)	A practical introduction to good development practices, order-of-accuracy, numerical differentiation, integration, interpolation, ODEs, root finding, solving hyperbolic, elliptical, and parabolic PDEs, and parallel programming, with examples in python. (S 2013)

Python for Scientific Computing

(grad special topics)

A one-hour weekly graduate seminar that introduces python and a

variety of libraries (NumPy, matplotlib, SciPy, SymPy) for numerical analysis, visualization, and data processing, as well as basic soft-

Other Teaching Experience:

Summer 2001	University of Chicago / Department of Computer Science:
	Teaching assistant for the Introduction to Programming in C class in the Computer Science Professional Masters Program at the University of Chicago.
1997–1998	Center of Astronomical Research in Antarctica (CARA) outreach program:
	Developed and taught thermodynamics, E&M, and mechanics experiments to grade 7–12 Chicago school students. Awarded the Carl Sagan teaching award.
1996–1997	Introductory Physics Teaching Assistant (University of Chicago):
	Taught weekly discussion and laboratory sections. Awarded the Gregor Wentzel teaching award.

Professional Development:

2001	Finite Volume Upwind and Centered Methods for Hyperbolic Conservation Laws (Barcelona, Spain)
1999	NASA Summer School for High Performance Computational Earth and Space Sciences

Stony Brook University Service:

2013–	Astronomy Open Nights coordinator, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2011–12, 2013–	Strategic Advising Committee, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2013–14	Undergraduate Astronomy Coordinator, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2014–15	Department Chair Search Committee, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2014–15	Three-year Reappointment Committee for Astronomy colleague, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2013–14	Tenure Committee for Astronomy colleague, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2013–14	Astronomy Faculty Search Committee, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2013	Ad-hoc Committee for High-Energy Physics Hire, Dept. Physics and Astronomy
2007–12	Colloquium Committee, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy (chair: Fall 2008, Fall 2009, Fall 2010, Fall 2011)
2011	CESAME/Physics and Astronomy joint hire committee, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2010	Teaching Learning Technology (TLT) Advisory Committee
2009	Long Range Planning Committee, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2007-09	Graduate Advising Committee, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2006–09	University Senate Committee on Computing and Communications (chair: Feb. 2008 – May 2009)

2008	Department Chair Search Committee, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2007–08	Astronomy Faculty Search Committee, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2006–07	Graduate Admission Committee, Dept. of Physics and Astronomy
2006–07	NYCCS Faculty Search Committee (Dept. level), Dept. of Physics and Astronomy

Professional Service:

	Elected to the OLCF User Group Executive Board (Vice chair: 2014–15; Chair: 2015–16)
N	Referee for the Astrophysical Journal, Astronomy and Astrophysics, Nature, Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Journal of Computational Physics, and Nuclear Physics A
	Annual <i>Astronomy Open Night</i> public outreach talks, Stony Brook (Open Night coordinator from Fall 2013–)
2014 E	External reviewer for NSF PRAC
2013 S	Served on a NASA ATP grant review panel
2013 E	External reviewer for NSF Office of Cyber Infrastructure
	Reviewer for the Great Lakes Consortium for Petascale Computation (2012) proposals for the NCSA Blue Waters machine.
2011 E	External reviewer for DOE Office of Nuclear Physics
	External reviewer for NASA Astrophysics Theory and Fundamental Physics Program
2006 S	Served on NSF Astronomy and Astrophysics Program review panel

Meeting Organization:

2015	Scientific organizing committee for the workshop <i>GNASH</i> : <i>The anomalous metal- poor stars and convective-reactive nuclear astrophysics</i> (U. Victoria, Victoria, BC)
2015	Co-organizer of the <i>New York Area Computational Astrophysics meeting</i> (Farmingdale State College, April 2015)
2014–2015	Organizing committee for the 2015 <i>Oak Ridge Leadership Computing Facility User Meeting</i>
2012–2013	Local organizing committee for the <i>National Nuclear Physics Summer School</i> (NNPSS 2013).
2012	Co-convener of <i>Thermonuclear explosions: Type Ias, Novae, and X-ray bursts</i> working group at <i>Nuclear Astrophysics Town Meeting</i> (Detroit, MI)

Astrophysical Software / Other Projects:

ongoing Creator of the Open Astrophysics Bookshelf github organization http://open-astrophysics-bookshelf.github.io/ and author of the open text Compu-

tational Hydrodynamics for Astrophysics

ongoing Co-developer of the publicly-available low Mach number hydrodynamics code

Maestro, http://bender.astro.sunysb.edu/Maestro/

ongoing Co-developer of the publicly-available compressible hydrodynamics code Cas-

tro, https://ccse.lbl.gov/Downloads/downloadCASTRO.html

ongoing Developed and distribute many simple teaching codes (advection, Eulerian

compressible and incompressible hydro solvers, multigrid, etc., with accompanying notes and exercises), http://www.astro.sunysb.edu/mzingale/software/

ongoing Created a library of astronomy animations introducing basic concepts (e.g.

Kepler's laws, blackbody radiation, waves, binary star/exoplanet dynamics, etc.) as well as more advanced concepts (e.g. entropy in convection), http://www.astro.sunysb.edu/mzingale/software/astro/, also available on youtube,

http://www.youtube.com/user/michaelzingale

ongoing Contributor to the astrophysics visualization package yt

1997–2002 Original member of the FLASH Code development team

Guest Appointments:

2000–2003 Guest Appointment at Argonne National Laboratory / Mathematics and Com-

puter Science Division

April 2001 Guest at the Max-Planck-Institut für Astrophysik

Professional Societies:

Member of the American Association of Physics Teachers Member of the American Astronomical Society Member of the American Physical Society

Students Advised:

graduate Chris Malone (Stony Brook, PhD 2011, thesis: Multidimensional

Simulations of Convection Preceding a Type Ia X-ray Bursts)

Adam Jacobs (Stony Brook, current student, working on Maestro

simulations of sub-Chandrasekhar mass SNe Ia)

Max Katz (Stony Brook, current student, working on Castro sim-

ulations of white dwarf mergers)

undergraduate Max Katz (REU student at Stony Brook, summer 2010, worked

on generating initial models with the MESA code)

Adam Siegel (Stony Brook, BS 2011, worked on flame modeling)

Ryan Orvedahl (Stony Brook, BS 2013, worked on Maestro algorithm issues and particle analysis) $\,$

References:

references available upon request